<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/football/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/football/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2023-03-31T15:43:51+13:00</updated><id>/football/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Football Notes</title><subtitle>Notes taken on journet as an amateur football player and coach.
</subtitle><author><name>Roberto Allende</name></author><entry><title type="html">Fast! Play fast</title><link href="/football/2023/03/30/play-fast-football.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fast! Play fast" /><published>2023-03-30T00:00:00+13:00</published><updated>2023-03-30T00:00:00+13:00</updated><id>/football/2023/03/30/play-fast-football</id><content type="html" xml:base="/football/2023/03/30/play-fast-football.html"><![CDATA[<p>Playing slowly allows your opponent to get organized, which often leads to turnovers and ultimately, losses. Avoiding slow play is crucial for winning games. So, what does it mean to play fast?</p>

<!--more-->

<hr />

<p>Watch the following video to see fast football in action:</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Fcj67F4zkig?start=34" frameborder="0"></iframe>

<p>Playing fast in football does not necessarily require long balls. Rather, it means moving the ball quickly. Nothing in football is faster than a moving ball - even the fastest player on the field cannot cover fifty meters as fast as a kicked ball. In Messi’s goal, it takes only five seconds for the ball to travel from midfield to the net.</p>

<p>Another beautiful goal</p>
<iframe width="100%" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mMiL4_1Yewg" frameborder="0"></iframe>

<p>Messi’s incredible dribbling skills are also a great example of playing fast, but it took 19-year-old Messi up to ten seconds to carry the ball from midfield to the net in his goal. While it’s impressive, not everyone can dribble past half of the opposing team in just ten seconds and score a goal.</p>

<p>So, fast football doesn’t necessarily require long balls or superhuman dribbling speed. Simple touches can achieve the same outcome. One or two-touch football can result in a goal in less than ten seconds, without the big error margin that comes with dribbling or long balls. Check out the following example.</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/gm3jomzFEpk" frameborder="0"></iframe>

<h1 id="play-fast-not-in-a-hurry">Play fast, not in a hurry</h1>
<p>Check out this video where a team plays fast, not in a hurry. They move the ball with patience, looking for the gap in the defense.</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/iBZdcpdxoTA" frameborder="0"></iframe>

<p>Playing fast typically means playing at a high tempo or pace, where the player is focused on moving quickly and efficiently without sacrificing control or accuracy.</p>

<p>On the other hand, playing in a hurry typically implies a sense of panic or urgency, where the player is rushing their decisions or movements without proper control or strategy.</p>

<h1 id="totally-possible">Totally Possible</h1>

<p>This is totally possible in Amateur and Junior Football. Watch the following goals.</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wlb2h_cyhQ8" frameborder="0"></iframe>

<p>It takes about five seconds from midfield to the end of the net. These players are eight years old.</p>

<p>Another one. Different team. Same coach.</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Yw1qA9vl7Uo" frameborder="0"></iframe>

<p>These players are 11 years old.</p>

<p>Same team, two years before.</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/juQ7XE0Qp9g" frameborder="0"></iframe>

<h1 id="how-to-play-fast-and-win-games">How to Play Fast and Win Games</h1>
<p>To play fast, you must have the desire to do so. It’s a decision that needs to be made before the game starts. You need to consciously choose to play at a high tempo, limiting your touches on the ball to maintain quick play. Dribbling is a great resource, but it should be the exception, not the rule. If you want to play fast and get the job done, use one touch instead of two. If you can accomplish it in two touches, avoid taking three. The more touches you need to control and pass the ball, the slower your progress will be.</p>

<p>Another way to think about speed in football is through what <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Soccer-IQ-Things-Smart-Players/dp/1469982471">Dan Blank</a> calls the <em>football speed ladder</em>:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The <strong>slowest</strong> way to move the ball in football is when a player dribbles while making lateral movements and feints.</li>
  <li><strong>Slow</strong> play is when a player runs straight ahead with the ball at top speed.</li>
  <li><strong>Faster</strong> is a player running without the ball.</li>
  <li>The <strong>fastest</strong> football is a moving ball.</li>
</ul>

<p>Speed of play is more than a habit - it’s a lifestyle. You can only fully embrace it when you realize that nothing is more important than quick play. In football, fast is better than slow, and it’s ultimately what wins games.</p>

<hr />

<div class="fb-comments" data-href="https://en.allende.nz/football/2023/03/30/play-fast-football.html" data-width="720" data-numposts="10"></div>]]></content><author><name>Roberto Allende</name></author><category term="Speed" /><category term="Passes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Playing slowly allows your opponent to get organized, which often leads to turnovers and ultimately, losses. Avoiding slow play is crucial for winning games. So, what does it mean to play fast?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introducing Astuten</title><link href="/football/2022/07/08/introducing-astuten.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing Astuten" /><published>2022-07-08T00:00:00+12:00</published><updated>2022-07-08T00:00:00+12:00</updated><id>/football/2022/07/08/introducing-astuten</id><content type="html" xml:base="/football/2022/07/08/introducing-astuten.html"><![CDATA[<p>As a grassroots football coach I want to make sure I give fair playing time to every player on my team. That’s why I used to spend hours planning game subs.</p>

<!--more-->

<hr />

<p>Planning subs is not easy because it’s not just about playing time. You also want to rotate positions but not that often. You want to optimise learning opportunities given the difficulty an opponents provides and so on.</p>

<p>More than once occasion, I showed up to a match with perfect plan just to get a phone call from a parent telling me that his child couldn’t play that day and now I had came up with new plan in just few minutes.</p>

<p>Every time I made a plan or I had to make a last minute adjustment I thought the must be a better way to do this.</p>

<p>And that’s why I developed <a href="http://astuten.io">Astuten</a>.</p>

<p>Astuten has three simple goals:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Allow coaches to make player substitution plans in seconds.</li>
  <li>Manage and follow lineups in real-time during matches.</li>
  <li>All in one app and across all your web browsers and devices.</li>
</ul>

<p>Are you curious? watch the demo video below and <a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSfTtaY7r3weo9R1vck9kZiDV991VF7vDHy3X1qVdC5DwYwdIQ/viewform">join the beta</a> to try it yourself.</p>

<iframe width="840" height="630" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ayRMwlBseJg" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Astuten is a live project so, if you find a feature that the app must have, don’t hesitate to write me. I want to make Astuten as much as useful for you as it’s for myself.</p>

<hr />

<div class="fb-comments" data-href="https://en.allende.nz/football/2022/07/09/introducing-astuten.html" data-width="720" data-numposts="10"></div>]]></content><author><name>Roberto Allende</name></author><category term="Coach" /><category term="Lineup" /><category term="MobileApp" /><category term="Astuten" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As a grassroots football coach I want to make sure I give fair playing time to every player on my team. That’s why I used to spend hours planning game subs.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Expectations for a Junior Football Journey</title><link href="/football/2022/06/07/expectations-for-a-junior-football-journey.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Expectations for a Junior Football Journey" /><published>2022-06-07T00:00:00+12:00</published><updated>2022-06-07T00:00:00+12:00</updated><id>/football/2022/06/07/expectations-for-a-junior-football-journey</id><content type="html" xml:base="/football/2022/06/07/expectations-for-a-junior-football-journey.html"><![CDATA[<p>A child dribbles the ball and breaks the opponent’s defence and now he/she is in front of the goalkeeper and has to resolve the situation in a few milliseconds.</p>

<p>The player misses. Is it bad?. The player scores. Is it good?.</p>

<p>There are countless situations like this in a game like a football. Situations that not only belong to the game itself but also about the relationship with teammates, adversity, and authority, just to mention a few.</p>

<!--more-->

<hr />

<p>From the sideline, adults watch and guide the children playing the game and after every situation, we may wonder what is the role of the adult after the match for each case? Should the adult intervene or not? For example, should we point out what is the right way to solve the problem? Should we keep silent and let the child figure it out on his/her own? Should we think nothing of the issue because is just a game?</p>

<p>In <em><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cPrdgWwbGMQ">Conversations about the Future</a>,</em> Pep Guardiola says:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Sports were the most useful learning tool that I had as a child. Through Sports, I learned to accept defeat, I learned there are others better than myself, I learned to come back after defeats, and I learned that coach may say that today I won’t play because I had bad behavior. I learned all the basic dynamics of human relationships.
But I’ve not learned these by imposition but by observing, experimenting, or sharing situations. That’s why I think that group sports have more potential than individual sports. In group sports I’ve to interact with people.</p>

  <p>Through sports, I learned that today I’ve to make an effort for you and I know that tomorrow you’ll make an effort for me because we want to achieve a common goal.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Football is just a game, but based on Pep’s experience and a few research publications, it’s also a <em>learning opportunity</em>.</p>

<p>If we assume learning is an important criterion in junior coaching we may wonder if it is the only one or if we think in general terms, what is success.</p>

<p><img src="/football/images/guardiola-trueba.jpg" alt="Sports were the most useful learning tool that I had as a child says Guardiola in Conversations about the Future" />
<em>Sports were the most useful learning tool that I had as a child says Guardiola in Conversations about the Future</em></p>

<h2 id="success">Success</h2>

<p>One of the best ways I found to define what is success in junior sports is the one written by Denis Ford in <em>Coaching junior Soccer</em>. Ford defines a process as successful when the child returns the following year to keep playing.</p>

<p>This is a recursive definition and encourages people to practice a sport for their entire life, which is a great ideal but to me, it feels a bit short because it doesn’t say much more. There are dynamics, experiences, and learnings that occur during different life stages of the players.</p>

<p>A few years later, I had the chance to meet a group of young adults that have been playing together since childhood and I found that building lifelong friends through sports is a very noble goal.</p>

<p>If a group of children practices football from the age of six to adulthood, they not only keep coming every year and they learn but they build lifelong friendships. What a better gift we can give to our children than teammates or friends for their entire life.</p>

<p>Note that school provides a similar opportunity but there’s a key difference. Football is a game, everything occurs around a ludic experience whether a school is a more complex process.</p>

<p>I omit the profession children will pick as adults because I don’t believe junior sports should pay attention on generating elite athetles. That’s an outcome, if it’s achieved, fine, if not fine too. There are several reasons for me to believe this, one of them is that <a href="https://sportnz.org.nz/media/2374/developing-participants-athletes-sports-leaders-oct-2017.pdf">Childhood success is not a reliable predictor of future success</a>.</p>

<h2 id="expectations">Expectations</h2>

<p>A football team is part of <a href="https://www.bnujfc.co.nz/faq">a club</a>, <a href="https://www.nzfootball.co.nz/juniors">a federation</a>, and a country. There are implicit and explicit codes that must be followed. The game occurs around the <a href="https://www.capitalfootball.org.nz/GET-INVOLVED-1/Competition-Information-1/Competition-Information-4">Law of the Game</a>, which has to be followed as well.</p>

<p>Beyond these and if we get into the details of the coaching process, I believe there are two very specific points worth mentioning: <em>equal playing time</em> and <em>position rotation</em>.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, I lived my childhood before Torbjørn Lorentzen wrote <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/23265507.2016.1266694?scroll=top&amp;needAccess=true&amp;"><em>Allocation of playing time within team sports – a problem for discussion</em></a>, so when I was nine years old I had coaches that would left me on the bench for entire games or they would tell me not to bother to come to a match because I wouldn’t play. So, I don’t have to read books to know why is important to take care of every player’s playing time. On the other extreme, I’ve seen coaches taking a clock and making subs on the exact number of seconds that would dictate the maths.</p>

<p>From the learning perspective, I believe the second criteria may be as bad as the first. It’s obvious that if a player doesn’t play, the player won’t learn and frustration may be high. Now, <em>playing time</em> is a bit more complex than time on the field, more explicitly, position matters. It’s not the same to play as a goalkeeper or striker or as a defender.</p>

<p>Even at a young age, there are players with a predisposition to different positions. A goalkeeper, for example, is the last in the line. A goalkeeper mistake may easily end up in an opponent’s goal whereas a midfielder mistake may not be that serious in terms of the outcome. Then, it’s not the same to make a player play as a goalkeeper few minutes and then as a striker. And this is a very personal thing, every player is unique and will experience different positions in different ways.</p>

<p>And it’s not as simple as keeping players in the same position because from the mathematical point of view, the combinatorial problem of the substitutions is so complex that is impossible to find a way to substitute players to guarantee equal playing time and at the same time, assure that players will play in the same positions during a match.</p>

<p>Solution: fair playing time. I heard this phrase from NZ Men’s U17 Coach and Youth Talent Pathway Manager Martin Bullock and I adopted it as my own. In my own adaptation, the idea is to get as close as possible to equal playing time but keeping in mind players’ positions in such a way that if a player goes to the bench and returns in the same match, the player will play in the same position.</p>

<p>Still is not a simple math problem to solve and that’s why I’ve been working during the last three years in <a href="https://astuten.io">a mobile app</a> to assist me with it, but that’s a story for another post.</p>

<p>Back to expectations, the other criteria I mentioned before is position rotation. As I said before, I don’t think is a good idea to rotate positions within a match so I prefer to rotate just a few times during a season. Position rotation is a must. This is a long subject too and very qualified people  gave very good explanations about this. For now let’s just say that early specialisation is not good and every player should be able to play at least two or three different positions on the field.</p>

<h2 id="context">Context</h2>

<p>So many words and I still didn’t say much about the conversation after a child scores or misses in front of the goalpost.</p>

<p>So, let’s put that event in context. The junior journey takes about seven years. Junior Football goes from six to thirteen years old. From seven to eight, the team has five players on the field. From nine to ten, seven. From eleven to twelve, nine. From thirteen years old, players play eleven a side.</p>

<p>The journey is long. Does it matter if a child scores or misses a goal when the player is nine years old?</p>

<p>To me it does because <em>football is the most important of the least important things</em> but what is the best intervention?. Well… if I could answer that question in a few words or even in one post, I wouldn’t need my football notes.</p>

<p>To be continued.</p>

<hr />

<p>Drawing: <strong>A Team of Friends</strong> by <a href="https://www.artstation.com/pabloestevez">Pablo Estevez</a>. Idea by Roberto Allende.</p>

<hr />

<div class="fb-comments" data-href="https://en.allende.nz/football/2022/06/07/expectations-for-a-junior-football-journey.html" data-width="720" data-numposts="10"></div>]]></content><author><name>Roberto Allende</name></author><category term="Coach" /><category term="Expectations" /><category term="Success" /><category term="JuniorPath" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A child dribbles the ball and breaks the opponent’s defence and now he/she is in front of the goalkeeper and has to resolve the situation in a few milliseconds. The player misses. Is it bad?. The player scores. Is it good?. There are countless situations like this in a game like a football. Situations that not only belong to the game itself but also about the relationship with teammates, adversity, and authority, just to mention a few.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A common ground for amateur football</title><link href="/football/2021/09/25/a-common-ground-for-amateur-football.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A common ground for amateur football" /><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+12:00</published><updated>2021-09-25T00:00:00+12:00</updated><id>/football/2021/09/25/a-common-ground-for-amateur-football</id><content type="html" xml:base="/football/2021/09/25/a-common-ground-for-amateur-football.html"><![CDATA[<p>Many things make football a fun game. Bielsa would say it’s because <em>the weak can defeat the powerful</em>. While watching a Rugby match, my friends would say that it’s because <em>football rules are very simple and easy to understand</em>.  “El Diego” would say it’s because <em>life goes away</em>.</p>

<p>Whatever your favorite reason is, there’s always be a collective element in the game. Football is a collective sport and it requires a collective construction.</p>

<!--more-->

<hr />

<p>As a football enthusiast, such collective construction requires a common ground. If there is no consensus, conflict or frustration are the usual outcomes.</p>

<h1 id="its-about-values">It’s about values</h1>
<p>By common ground, I mean a set of values. These may be obvious or just ‘common sense’ but after many ‘after game’ conversations I found that the lack of consensus is very common among teams. 
For that reason, I think it is important to write them down and talk about them. If we are playing together, and I hope we do, these are the ones I believe in. If you don’t agree with them, it’s fine, let’s talk about it and find new common ground.</p>

<p>This is my list. They’re just four:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Team must be inclusive</li>
  <li>Don’t believe in good or bad, believe in growth</li>
  <li>Mistakes are allowed</li>
  <li>Play to win</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="1-a-team-must-be-inclusive">1. A team must be inclusive</h2>
<p>Assuming that</p>

<ul>
  <li>#1: A football team needs at least eleven, seven, or five players on the field and,</li>
  <li>#2: Every team has players with different levels.</li>
</ul>

<p>It simply does not make sense not to be inclusive. It’s a practical thing. Let me show the point with a few examples:</p>

<p>Let’s say Team A from Hypergalactic Empire Club is lucky enough to gather 15 young and very talented players to play in the <em>Earth Gravity League</em> of Mars Amateur Football Association. Because this is a team just for
stars, they exclude five players that want to join the team but they’re not good enough.</p>

<p>Season stars, Team A wins five matches in a row by at least a ten goals of difference until injuries become a serious thing. So, by the sixth match, the team plays without substitution at all. It’s still a win but because of a new injury in the match, Team A has to play most of the game with ten players. Before the seventh match, two players, who are brothers, decide to take a job in Jupiter and now, Hypergalactic Empire Club’s Team A has to default games.</p>

<p>Another example, it is common that junior leagues use five aside for a certain age, two years later, they use seven aside and later on nine aside, etc. Similar situation, if you stream <em>more gifted</em> players from the first year, you may experience similar problems as Hypergalactic Club has when the children grow and teams need two more players.</p>

<p>In a sentence, I believe that football must be inclusive because a team cannot afford the luxury of excluding people.</p>

<p>Of course, I believe being inclusive is the right thing to do but my point is that even from a pragmatic point of view it doesn’t make sense not to be.</p>

<h2 id="2-dont-believe-in-good-or-bad-believe-in-growth">2. Don’t believe in good or bad, believe in growth</h2>

<p>A professional team needs good and very talented players to win the Champions. If a coach doesn’t win matches, the coach will be sacked. Then winning is a must. The job of a lot of people depends on it.</p>

<p>Amateur football is different. At least, in theory, nobody will be fired if a team doesn’t win. It may not be fun and you may lose players if you don’t win <strong>but</strong> if there’s growth you may not win today
but eventually, you will and the best thing, the team will hold together even with bad scores.</p>

<p>Growth is a mindset. It’s about believing that anyone can improve. Bad or good is a mindset too, it’s called the <em>fixed mindset</em>, you are either good or bad. In the fixed mindset, imperfections are shameful.
The growth mindset says all of these things can be developed. All — you, teammates — are capable of growth and change.</p>

<p><img src="/football/images/mindset.jpg" alt="Change your mindset poster from Brooklyn Primary School" />
<em>Change your mindset poster from Brooklyn Primary School in Wellington, NZ</em></p>

<p>The mindset concept is not something new and there are plenty of people who researched and wrote about this topic. Just to mention one, <a href="https://www.brainpickings.org/2014/01/29/carol-dweck-mindset/">Maria Popova’s brainpickings</a> is a very quick introduction to the topic.</p>

<h2 id="3-mistakes-are-allowed">3. Mistakes are allowed</h2>

<p>If you believe in growth, mistakes must be allowed. A mistake is a great teacher. Sometimes is the only way to learn.</p>

<h2 id="4-play-to-win">4. Play to win</h2>

<p>In a sports game, the participant must stretch his/her skills to meet the challenge provided by the skills of the opponent. The roots of the word “compete” are the Latin <em>con petire</em>, which meant <em>to seek together.</em> What each person seeks is to actualize his/her potential.</p>

<p>Leaving the outcome aside means quitting the adventure to seek individual and collective potential.</p>

<p>I’ve met coaches, especially in the junior space, that <em>hide</em> the score from children because they don’t want to expose them to <em>toxic</em> situations. I agree that if players are not concerned about the score it doesn’t make sense to push them, but if they are aware, I think it is essential to take it as part of the game. Outcomes are a useful learning tool. It gives purpose to the game. It creates a sense of urgency.  It helps to learn how to deal with frustration. It helps players and coaches to be better and push boundaries.</p>

<p>And lastly, it creates situations where we may make mistakes and if we do, we learn.</p>

<hr />

<p><img src="/football/images/first-post-comments.jpg" alt="Comments in Disqus" /></p>

<div class="fb-comments" data-href="https://en.allende.nz/football/2021/09/25/a-common-ground-for-amateur-football.html" data-width="720" data-numposts="10"></div>]]></content><author><name>Roberto Allende</name></author><category term="TeamBuilding" /><category term="Values" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Many things make football a fun game. Bielsa would say it’s because the weak can defeat the powerful. While watching a Rugby match, my friends would say that it’s because football rules are very simple and easy to understand. “El Diego” would say it’s because life goes away. Whatever your favorite reason is, there’s always be a collective element in the game. Football is a collective sport and it requires a collective construction.]]></summary></entry></feed>